<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Blog | Mattes Groeger]]></title>
  <link href="http://MattesGroeger.github.io/blog/categories/blog/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://MattesGroeger.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-11-15T23:33:42+01:00</updated>
  <id>http://MattesGroeger.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Mattes Groeger]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[From Wordpress to Octopress]]></title>
    <link href="http://MattesGroeger.github.io/blog/2013/11/16/from-wordpress-to-octopress/"/>
    <updated>2013-11-16T12:07:00+01:00</updated>
    <id>http://MattesGroeger.github.io/blog/2013/11/16/from-wordpress-to-octopress</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>For a long time I wasn&rsquo;t happy with my <a href="http://www.wordpress.org">Wordpress</a> blog. Maintenance and hosting seemed unnecessary complex. When researching alternative solutions I found <a href="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</a>. In this article I highlight the reasons that made me switch.</p>

<!-- more -->


<h2>Problems with Wordpress</h2>

<p>Wordpress is a PHP website with a MySQL database. As the code is open source it makes it easy for someone to write and use exploits to compromise my blog. That&rsquo;s one reason why Wordpress and its plugins provide updates frequently. But even though I updated often I got a lot of spam comments. Even the captcha system I had in place didn&rsquo;t stop them.</p>

<p>It is very convient to write blog posts with Wordpress as it comes with a [WYSIWYG editor]. But that means also that the content is only residing on the server. In the worst case I could loose all my data if the server breaks. To avoid that I have to do backups of all files (images, videos, &hellip;) and the database itself.</p>

<p>If I want to change my blog design I have to setup everything locally. When done, I have to upload all changes via FTP. That&rsquo;s rather annoying. I wanted something that is hosted and deployed on GitHub.</p>

<h2>Benefits of Octopress</h2>

<ul>
<li>Static page generator</li>
<li><p>Website renders super fast as everything is static</p></li>
<li><p>Posts written in Markdown</p></li>
<li><p>Nice codeblock support</p></li>
<li><p>Clear and modern HTML5, scss for Stylesheets</p></li>
<li><p>I use a modified version of the <a href="https://github.com/lucaslew/whitespace">whitespace theme</a></p></li>
<li><p>Git provides with version history</p></li>
<li>1 step deploy (rake deploy)</li>
<li><p>Hosting on GitHub (github.io)</p></li>
<li><p>Comment system is provided by external service</p></li>
<li>Updating blog via command line</li>
</ul>


<h2>Conclusion</h2>

<p>One drawback is that you rely on external services. Imagine for some reason the comment provider stops his service. All your comments will be lost. I for myself rather take this risk in exchange for easier maintainance. I&rsquo;m pretty happy with Octopress. If you are interested, go and <a href="http://octopress.org/">check it out for yourself</a>.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
